Samuel Chagas de Assis

BIOTECHNOLOGIST - COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGIST

Campinas, São Paulo - Brazil

☑samuel.achagas98@gmail.com | ☆chagas98.github.io | ☑chagas98 | 圖samuelchagass

About me

I'm a computational biologist fascinated by understanding the molecular biodiversity and mechanisms. I have experience with workflow development in Python and R, molecular dynamics simulations data analysis, and immunogenetics. Currently, my work focuses on workflow development through documentation, automation, and reproducibility. I'm an intern researcher at the Computational Biocatalysis Group at LNBR/CNPEM in Brazil, where I work with specific Carbohydrate-Active Enzymes for microbiome and structural biology research projects using biomolecular modeling data and biochemical interpretation. In my free time, I enjoy running, reading about Latin culture, and cooking plant-based recipes.

Education

Federal University of Latin-American Integration (UNILA)

BACHELOR IN BIOTECHNOLOGY

Liberato Salzano Vieira da Cunha Foudation

ELECTRICAL TECHNICIAN

Foz do Iguaçu, Brazil

2018-2024

Novo Hamburgo, Brazil

2013-2017

Experience

Brazilian Center for Research in Energy and Materials (CNPEM)

Campinas, São Paul

COMPUTATIONAL BIOCATALYSIS INTERN

2023-Present

- I have performed data analysis of several molecular dynamics simulations, primarily using Python and Shell scripting compatible with SLURM HPC environment focusing in new insights about molecular mechanisms from a new Carbohydrate-Active enzyme family
- | Gromacs | SLURM/HPC | Python/MDAnalysis | Python/Autodock Vina | Conda/Bioconda | Pymol/VMD |

SporeData Inc. Remoto

FREELANCER - ANALISTA DE DADOS JÚNIOR

10.2022-02.2023

- Análise e visualização de dados em R (ggplot2, tidyverse, RStats, RMarkdown)
- Processamento de dados em nuvem (N3C)
- Reporting de dados de bioestatística para estudos clínicos

Parque Tecnológico Itaipu (PTI - Brasil)

Foz do Iguaçu, Paraná

2017-2018

- ESTÁGIO TÉCNICO EM ELETROTÉCNICA (720 HORAS)
- Auxiliar de Projetos ElétricosInstrumentação e Eficiência Energética

Habilidades e Qualificações _

- Linguagens de Programação: R, Python e Bash
- Markup: RMarkdown e HTML
- Gerenciamento: Git/GitHub, GitHub Actions, Slurm
- Sistemas UNIX/Linux

Comunicação_

Português Nativo

Inglês Intermediário à Avançado

Espanhol Intermediário

Prêmios

Primeiro Lugar. Menção Honrosa na área de Ciências da Saúde no XI EICTI - UNILA
Medalha de Ouro e Nomeação de Melhor Projeto de Nova Aplicação e Práticas Humanas na International Genetically Engineering Machine Competition (iGEM)
Melhor Projeto de Escolha do Público no V Curso de Verão de Engenharia de Máquinas Biológicas - UFMG
Melhor Apresentação no V Curso de Verão de Engenharia de Máquinas Biológicas - UFMG
Primeiro Lugar. Menção Honrosa na área de Tecnologia e Produção no VII SEUNI - UNILA
Menção Honrosa UNESCO pelo Projeto de Relevância Social na Conferência Internacional de Ciência e Tecnologia de Nível Médio - MOSTRATEC/UNESCO

Publicações

• **De Assis**, S.C., Morgado, D.L., Scheidt, D.T., De Souza, S.S., Cavallari, M.R., Ando, O.H.J., Carrilho, E. (2023). Review of Bacterial Nanocellulose-Based Electrochemical Biosensors: Functionalization, Challenges, and Future Perspectives. *MDPI Biosensors*, 13. https://doi.org/10.3390/bios13010142